Thank you very much. Well, I would like to start with testicles. Men who sleep
five hours a night have significantly smaller testicles than those who sleep
seven hours or more. In addition, men who routinely sleep just four to five
hours a night will have a level of testosterone, which is that of someone
ten years their senior. So a lack of sleep will age a man by a decade in terms of
that critical aspect of wellness. And we see equivalent impairments in female
reproductive health caused by a lack of sleep. This is the best news that I have
for you today. From this point, it may only get worse. Not only will I tell you
about the wonderfully good things that happen when you get sleep, but the
alarmingly bad things that happen when you don't get enough. Both for your
brain and for your body. Let me start with the brain and the functions of
learning and memory. Because what we've discovered over the past ten or so
years is that you need sleep after learning to essentially hit the save
button on those new memories so that you don't forget. But recently we
discovered that you also need sleep before learning. And now to actually
prepare your brain, almost like a dry sponge ready to initially soak up new
information. And without sleep, the memory circuits of the brain essentially
become waterlogged as it were and you can't absorb new memories. So let me show
you the data. Here in the study, we decided to test the hypothesis that pulling
the all-nighter was a good idea. So we took a group of individuals and we
assigned them to one of two experimental groups, a sleep group and a sleep
deprivation group. Now the sleep group, they're going to get a full eight hours
of slumber. But the deprivation group, we're going to keep them awake in the
laboratory under full supervision. There's no knaps or caffeine, by the way, so it's
miserable for everyone involved. And then the next day, we're going to place
those participants inside an MRI scanner. And we're going to have them try and
learn a whole list of new facts as we're taking snapshots of brain activity. And
then we're going to test them to see how effective that learning has been. And
that's what you're looking at here on the vertical axis. And when you put those
two groups head to head, what you find is a quite significant 40% deficit in the
ability of the brain to make new memories without sleep. I think this should be
concerning considering what we know is happening to sleep in our education
populations right now. In fact, to put that in context, it would be the difference
in a child acing an exam versus failing it miserably, 40%. And we've gone on to
discover what goes wrong within your brain to produce these types of
learning disabilities. And there's a structure that sits on the left and the
right side of your brain called the hippocampus. And you can think of the
hippocampus almost like the informational inbox of your brain. It's very good at
receiving new memory files and then holding on to them. And when you look at this
structure in those people who'd had a full night of sleep, we saw lots of
healthy learning-related activity. Yet in those people who were sleep deprived,
we actually couldn't find any significant signal whatsoever. So it's almost as
those sleep deprivation had shut down your memory inbox and any new incoming
files, they were just being bounced. You couldn't effectively commit new
experiences to memory. So that's the bad that can happen if I were to take
sleep away from you, but let me just come back to that control group for a
second. Do you remember those folks that got a full eight hours of sleep? Well, we
can ask a very different question. What is it about the physiological quality of
your sleep when you do get it that restores and enhances your memory and
learning ability each and every day? And by placing electrodes all over the head,
what we've discovered is that there are big powerful brainwaves that happen
during the very deepest stages of sleep that have riding on top of them, the
spectacular burst of electrical activity that we call sleep spindles. And it's
the combined quality of these deep sleep brainwaves that acts like a file
transfer mechanism at night. Shifting memories from a short-term vulnerable
reservoir to a more permanent long-term storage site within the brain. And
therefore protecting them, making them safe. And it is important that we
understand what during sleep actually transacts these memory benefits because
there are real medical and societal implications. And let me just tell you about
one area that we've moved this work out into clinically, which is the
context of aging and dementia. Because it's, of course, no secret that as we
get older, our learning and memory abilities begin to fade and decline. But what
we've also discovered is that a physiological signature of aging is that your
sleep gets worse, especially that deep quality of sleep that I was just
discussing. And only last year we finally published evidence that these two
things, they're not simply co-occurring. They are significantly interrelated.
And it suggests that the disruption of deep sleep is an under-appreciated
factor that is contributing to cognitive decline or memory decline. In aging
and most recently we've discovered in Alzheimer's disease as well. Now I know
this is remarkably depressing news. It's in the mail. It's coming at you. But
there's a potential silver lining here. Unlike many of the other factors that
we know are associated with aging. For example, changes in the physical
structure of the brain. That's fiendishly difficult to treat. But that sleep
is a missing piece in the explanatory puzzle of aging in Alzheimer's. Is
exciting because we may be able to do something about it. And one way that we
are approaching this at my sleep center is not by using sleeping pills, by the
way. Unfortunately, they are blunt instruments that do not produce
naturalistic sleep. Instead, we're actually developing a method based on this.
It's called direct current brain stimulation. You insert a small amount of
voltage into the brain. So small, you typically don't feel it. But it has a
measurable impact. Now, if you apply this stimulation during sleep in young
healthy adults, as if you're sort of singing in time with those deep sleep
brainwaves, not only can you amplify the size of those deep sleep brainwaves,
but in doing so, we can almost double the amount of memory benefit that you
get from sleep. The question now is whether we can translate the same
affordable, potentially portable piece of technology into older adults and
those with dementia. Can we restore back some healthy quality of deep sleep
and in doing so, can we salvage aspects of their learning and memory function?
That is my real hope now. That's one of our moon shot goals, as it were. So that's
an example of sleep for your brain, but sleep is just as essential for your body.
We've already spoken about sleep loss and your reproductive system. Or I could
tell you about sleep loss and your cardiovascular system and that all it takes
is one hour. Because there is a global experiment performed on 1.6 billion
people across 70 countries twice a year, and it's called Daylight Savings Time.
Now in the spring, when we lose one hour of sleep, we see a subsequent 24% increase
in heart attacks that following day. In the autumn, when we gain an hour of sleep,
we see a 21% reduction in heart attacks. Isn't that incredible? And you see
exactly the same profile for car crashes, road traffic accidents, even suicide rates.
But as a deeper dive, I want to focus on this sleep loss and your immune system. And here
I'll introduce these delightful blue elements in the image. They are called natural killer
cells. And you can think of natural killer cells almost like the secret service agents
of your immune system. And they are very good at identifying dangerous, unwanted elements
and eliminating them. In fact, what they're doing here is destroying a cancerous tumor mass.
So what you wish for is a virile set of these immune assassins at all times. And tragically
that's what you don't have if you're not sleeping enough. So here in this experiment, you're
not going to have your sleep deprived for an entire night. You're simply going to have
your sleep restricted to four hours for one single night. And then we're going to look
to see what's the percent reduction in immune cell activity that you suffer. And it's
not small, it's not 10%, it's not 20%, there was a 70% drop in natural killer cell activity.
It's a concerning state of immune deficiency. And you can perhaps understand why we're
now finding significant links between short sleep duration and your risk for the development
of numerous forms of cancer. Currently that list includes cancer of the bowel, cancer
of the prostate, and cancer of the breast. In fact, the link between a lack of sleep and
cancer is now so strong that the World Health Organization has classified any form of night-time
shift work as a probable carcinogen because of a disruption of your sleep weight rhythms.
So you may have heard of that old maxim that you can sleep when you're dead. Well,
I'm being quite serious now. It is mortally unwise advice. We know this from epidemiological
studies across millions of individuals. There's a simple truth. The shorter your sleep, the shorter
your life. Short sleep predicts all cause mortality. And if increasing your risk for the development
of cancer or even Alzheimer's disease, we're not sufficiently disquieting. We have since discovered
that a lack of sleep will even erode the very fabric of biological life itself, your DNA
genetic code. So here in this study, they took a group of healthy adults and they limited
them to six hours of sleep a night for one week. And then they measured the change in their gene
activity profile relative to when those same individuals were getting a full eight hours of sleep
a night. And there were two critical findings. First, a sizable and significant 711 genes were
distorted in their activity caused by a lack of sleep. The second result was that about half of those
genes were actually increased in their activity. The other half were decreased. Now, those genes that
were switched off by a lack of sleep were genes associated with your immune system. So once again,
you can see that immune deficiency. In contrast, those genes that were actually upregulated or
increased by way of a lack of sleep were genes associated with the promotion of tumors,
genes associated with long-term chronic inflammation within the body. And genes associated with
stress and as a consequence, cardiovascular disease. There is simply no aspect of your wellness
that can retreat at the sign of sleep deprivation and get away unscathed. It's rather like a broken
water pipe in your home. Sleep loss will leak down into every nook and cranny of your physiology.
Even tempering with the very DNA nucleic alphabet, that spells out your daily health narrative.
And at this point, you may be thinking, oh my goodness, how do I start to get better sleep? What are
your tips for good sleep? Well, beyond avoiding the damaging and harmful impact of alcohol and
caffeine on sleep. And if you're struggling with sleep at night avoiding naps during the day,
I have two pieces of advice for you. The first is regularity. Go to bed at the same time,
wake up at the same time. No matter whether it's the weekday or the weekend, regularity is king.
And it will anchor your sleep and improve the quantity and the quality of that sleep.
The second is keep it cool. Your body needs to drop its core temperature by about two to three
degrees Fahrenheit to initiate sleep and then to stay asleep. And it's the reason you will always
find it easier to fall asleep in a room that's too cold than too hot. So aim for a bedroom
temperature of around 65 degrees or about 18 degrees Celsius. That's going to be optimal for the
sleep of most people. And then finally in taking a step back then, what is the mission critical
statement here? Well, I think it may be this. Sleep unfortunately is not an optional lifestyle
luxury. Sleep is a non-negotiable biological necessity. It is your life support system. And it
is Mother Nature's best effort yet at immortality. And the decimation of sleep throughout industrialised
nations is having a catastrophic impact on our health or wellness, even the safety and the education
of our children. It's a silent sleep loss epidemic and it is fast becoming one of the greatest
public health challenges that we face in the 21st century. I believe it is now time for us to
reclaim our right to a full night of sleep and without embarrassment or that unfortunate stigma
of laziness. And in doing so, we can be reunited with the most powerful elixir of life,
the swiss army knife of health as it were. And with that soap box ran to over, I will simply say,
good night, good luck, and above all, I do hope you sleep well. Thank you very much indeed.
Thank you. Thank you so much. No, no, no, stay there for a second. Good job not running away,
though. I appreciate that. That was terrifying. You're welcome. Yes. Thank you. Thank you.
Since we can't catch up on sleep, what are we supposed to do? What do we do when we're like
tossing and turning in bed late at night or doing shift work or whatever else? So you're right,
we can't catch up on sleep. Sleep is not like the bank. You can't accumulate a debt and then
hope to pay it off at a later point in time. I should also note the reason that it's so catastrophic
that our health deteriorates so quickly. First is because human beings are the only species that
deliberately deprive themselves of sleep for no apparent reason. As we're smart. And I make that
point because what it means is that mother nature throughout the course of evolution has never had
to face the challenge of this thing called sleep deprivation. So she's never developed a safety net.
And that's why when you under sleep, things just sort of implode so quickly both within the
brain and the body. So you just have to prioritize. Okay. So but tossing and turning in bed,
what do I do? So if you are staying in bed awake for too long, you should get out of bed and go to
a different room and do something different. The reason is because your brain will very quickly
associate your bedroom with the place of wakefulness. And you need to break that association.
So only return to bed when you are sleepy. And that way you will relearn the association that
you once had, which is your bed is the place of sleep. So the analogy would be you'd never sit at
the dinner table waiting to get hungry. So why would you lie in bed waiting to get sleepy?
All right. Well, thank you for that wake-up call. Great job, Matt.
Very welcome. Thank you very much.